A Guide to the John Steinbeck Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6239-e
John Steinbeck Collection 1934-1962
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6239-e
16 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit [ 1963 Dec 17 ] 1966 Jan 24
Item Listing
- Letters
  - John Steinbeck to Wilbur Needham, [1934] Apr 4; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Discusses Needham as a critic, critics in general and use of man's unconscious in his current series of books, particularly [
    To a God Unknown
    ].]
  - John Steinbeck to Wilbur Needham, [1935 Feb 7]; TLS, 2 p. w/env
    [Discusses writing the final draft of a novel [
    In Dubious Battle
    ], the effect of the loss of one sense upon the others, and Covici-Friede's interest in his work; briefly discusses Needham's deafness, [Ludvig van] Beethoven, having lived in Glendale,
    Tortilla Flat
    , [Pascal] Covici, [Robert Oleson] Ballou, Paul Jordan-Smith, [William] Heineman publishing
    , shorts published in
    The North American Review
    and English magazines,
    Cup of Gold
    , his work requiring "abolish[ing] every vestige of ego," places he would show him were Needham to visit, a plan of work which would require remaking the novel and appreciation for his interest in his work; mentions Pacific Grove, New York City, London, Mexico,
    Paradise Lost
    , Lucifer and Monterey. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Wilbur Needham, [1935 Fall]; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    [Discusses a visit to Mexico City, a dog in Tamazunchale, beggars, Gerald Fitzgerald having some manuscripts Jake Luther wants to print and his desire that Luther get some better things from McIntosh Otis [Literary Agency]; briefly discusses the death of his father, John Ernst Steinbeck and a book [
    ]; mentions Puebla, Pacific Grove, Paseo de la Reforma, Chapultepec and New York City. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Bob Crosby, [1935 Oct 22]; APCS
    [Discusses a trip to Mexico; briefly discusses Crosby's liking "that book," Crosby's illness, lack of a picture, not knowing Texas but liking New Mexico, a mountain rainstorm and an upcoming ceremony at the pyramids of Teotihuacan; mentions Chapultepec. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Wilbur Needham, [1936 Jan 3]; APCS
    [Discusses a forwarded manuscript, needed house repairs, recent return from a trip [to Mexico] and a new book [
  - John Steinbeck to Wilbur Needham, [1936 Feb 12]; APCS
    [Discusses a "tampered" review, a review in
    The Worker
    , [ Carol Henning Steinbeck's ] influenza, changes to the house, a new book [
    ] and his current work [
    Of Mice and Men
  - John Steinbeck to Wilbur Needham, [1936 May 26]; APCS
    [Discusses writing for the theater, a book [
    In Dubious Battle,
    ], [
    ], his current work [
    ], Carol Henning Steinbeck's building a new house in Los Gatos, a trip to collect marine specimen, Needham as a reviewer and death of the novel; mentions Enseneda, California, Los Angeles and Santa Monica. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Wilbur Needham, [1938 Oct 4]; APCS
    [Discusses a review by Needham, "this blasted book" [
    The Grapes of Wrath
    ] and the rapid passing of time.]
  - John Steinbeck to [Merle] Armitage, 1939 Feb 17; ALS, 1 p.
    [Discusses [Edgard] Varese's interest in his work from a musical standpoint and the
    Grapes of Wrath
    as a "symphony"; briefly discusses where he and Armitage first met and his health; mentions Edward [Henry] Weston, Ritchie Lovejoy, Eagle Rock and The Viking Press. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Wilbur [Needham], [1939 Jun 6]; TL, 1 p. w/env
    [Discusses reviews by Needham and Larry [ Lawrence Clark Powell] in [
    Black & White
    ], a back injury, [ Harry Thornton] Moore's account of his work and Will Geer's interest in Ella Winter; mentions Hollywood. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Wilbur [Needham], [1939 Dec]; ALS, 1 p.
    [Discusses critics "beginning to work me over," a "nightmarish year," his pictures [
    and
    ] and preparation for next year's work,
    . ]
  - John Steinbeck to [Merle] Armitage, 1940 May 10; ALS, 1 p.
    [Discusses not wanting his letter printed, a hectic life and the war [World War II].]
  - John Steinbeck to Wilbur [Needham], [1940 Sep 28]; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Discusses biology as an escape from the "insane" world of men, whom he compares to lemmings; sees [World War II] as a species pattern not unlike bees; briefly discusses a trip to New York, being very busy, his defeatist attitude, avoiding politics and the "invertebrate book" [
    Sea of Cortez
    ]; mentions [Wendall Lewis] Willkie and Norway. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Merle [Armitage], 1941 Dec 31; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses his refusal to do a forward to Edward [Henry] Weston's book [
    Fifty Photographs: Edward Weston
    ], life in Eagle Rock. ]
  - John Steinbeck to H. Kauti, 1953 Feb 16; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses some lost slips and lack of a picture.]
  - John Steinbeck to Merle Armitage, 1958 Dec 1; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses the French liking for
    The Short Reign of Pippin IV
    , [Charles] de Gaulle's upsurge causing censor problems for a proposed French movie of it and French humor versus American humor; mentions [ Isabelle Heyman Armitage] and [World War II].]